in earlier videos, I have
在前面的视频中  (字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
said over and over that, when
我不止一次地说过
you are developing machine learning system,
在你开发机器学习系统时
one of the most valuable resources is
你最宝贵的资源
your time as the developer
就是你的时间
in terms of picking what
作为一个开发者
to work on next.
你需要正确选择下一步的工作
Or, you have a team of developers
或者也许你有一个开发团队
or a team of engineers working together
或者一个工程师小组
on a machine learning system, again
共同开发一个机器学习系统
one of the most valuable resources is
同样 最宝贵的还是
the time of the engineers or the developers working on the system.
开发系统所花费的时间
And what you really want to
你需要尽量避免的
avoid is that you or
情况是你或者
your colleagues or your friends spend
你的同事 你的朋友
a lot of time working on
花费了大量时间
some component, only to realize
在某一个模块上
after weeks or months of
在几周甚至几个月的努力以后
time spent, that all that
才意识到所有这些付出的劳动
work, you know, just doesn't
都对你最终系统的表现
make a huge difference on the performance of the final system.
并没有太大的帮助
In this video, what I'd
在这段视频中
like to to is, to talk about something called ceiling analysis.
我将介绍一下关于上限分析(ceiling analysis)的内容
When you or your team
当你自己或你跟
are working on a pipeline
你的团队在设计某个
machine learning system, this can
机器学习系统的流水线时
sometimes give you a very
这种方式通常能
strong signal, a very strong
提供一种很有价值的信号
guidance, on what parts
或者说很有用的导向
of the pipeline might be the best use of your time to work on.
告诉你流水线中的哪个部分最值得你花时间去完成
To talk about ceiling analysis, I'm
为了介绍上限分析
going to keep on using the
我将继续使用之前用过的
example of the photo
照片OCR流水线的例子
OCR pipeline and I said
在之前的课程中
earlier each of these
我讲过这些方框
boxes text detection, character
文字检测、字符分割
segmentation, character recognition, each
字符识别
of these boxes can have even
这每一个方框都可能
a small engineering team working
需要一个小团队来完成
on it, or maybe the
当然也可能
entire system is just built
你一个人来构建整个系统
by you, either way, but
不管怎样
the question is, where should you allocate resources?
问题是 你应该怎样分配资源呢？
Which of these boxes is
哪一个方框最值得
most worth your efforts, trying
你投入精力去做
to improve the performance of.
投入时间去改善效果
In order to explain the idea
（以下这段同前重复，译者注）
of ceiling analysis, I'm going
为了解释上限分析的原理
to keep using the example of our photo OCR pipeline.
我将继续使用照片OCR流水线的例子
As I mentioned earlier, each of
在之前的视频中我讲过
these boxes here, each of
这里的每个方框
these machine learning components could be
都表示一个机器学习的组成部分
the work of even a
需要一个小团队来完成
small team of engineers, or
当然也可能
maybe the whole system could be built by just one person.
整个系统都由一个人来完成
But the question is, where should
但问题是
you allocate scarce resources?
你应该如何分配资源呢？
Now this, which of these
也就是说
components, or which one or
这些模块中
two or maybe all three of these components
哪一个 或者哪两个、三个
is most worth your time
是最值得你花更多的
to try to improve the performance of.
精力去改善它的效果的？
So here's the idea of ceiling analysis.
这便是上限分析要做的事
As in the development process for
跟其他机器学习系统的
other machine learning systems as
开发过程一样
well, in order to make
为了决定
decisions on what to do
要开发这个系统应该
for developing the system
采取什么样的行动
is going to be
一个有效的方法是
very helpful to have a
对学习系统使用一个
single road number evaluation metric for this learning system.
数值评价量度
So let's say we pick characters level accuracy.
所以假如我们用字符准确度作为这个量度
So if, you know, given a
因此 给定一个
test set image, while just
测试样本图像
a fraction of alphabets of
那么这个数值就表示
characters in the testing image that
我们对测试图像中的文字
we recognize correctly.
识别正确的比例
Or you can pick some other single world
或者你也可以选择
number evaluation metric, if you
其他的某个数值评价度量值
want, but let's say that
随你选择
whatever evaluation metric we
但不管选择什么评价量度值
pick, we get that, we
我们只是假设
find that the overall system currently has 72% accuracy.
整个系统的估计准确率为72%
So, in other
所以换句话说
words, we have some set
我们有一些测试集图像
of test set images and for
并且对测试集中的
each test set images, we
每一幅图像
run it through text section, then
我们都对其分别运行
character 7 nation, then character
文字检测、字符分割
recognition, and we find
然后字符识别
that on our test set, the
然后我们发现
overall accuracy of the
整个测试集的准确率是72%
entire system was 72% on one of the metric you chose.
不管你用什么度量值来度量
Now just the idea behind
下面是上限分析的
sealing analysis which is that
主要思想
we're going to go to let
首先我们关注
see the first module of a
这个机器学习流程中的
machinery pipelines text detection.
第一个模块 文字检测
And what we are going
而我们要做的
to do is we are going to
实际上是在
monkey around with the test set.
给测试集样本捣点儿乱
We are going to go to the
我们要对
test set and for every test example
每一个测试集样本
we are just going to provide it
都给它提供一个
the correct text detection outputs.
正确的文字检测结果
In other words, we are going
换句话说
to the test set and just
我们要遍历每个测试集样本
manually tell the algorithm
然后人为地告诉算法
where the text is
每一个测试样本中
in each of the test examples.
什么地方出现了文字
So in other words, we
因此换句话说
are going to simulate what happens
我们是要仿真出
if we have a text detection
如果是100%
system with a 100%
正确地检测出
accuracy, for the purpose
图片中的文字信息
of detecting text in an image.
应该是什么样的
And really the way you
当然 要做到这个
do that is very simple right, instead
是很容易的
of letting your learning algorithm
现在不用你的学习算法
detect the text in the images.
来检测图像中的文字了
You wouldn't say go to the
你只需要找到对应的图像
images and just manually label what
然后人为地识别出
is the location of the text in my test set image.
测试集图像中出现文字的区域
And you would then let these
然后你要做的就是让这些
correct, so let these ground
绝对正确的结果
true labels of where as
这些绝对为真的标签
the text be part of
也就是告诉你
your text set and use these
图像中哪些位置
ground true labels what you
有文字信息的标签
feed in to the next
把它们传给下一个模块
stage of the pipeline, to the character segmentation pipeline.
也就是传给字符分割模块
So just said it again, by
我再说一遍
putting a checkmark over here,
这里打钩的地方
what I mean is Im going
我想做的是
to go to my test set and
遍历我的测试集
just give it the correct answers,
直接向它公布“标准答案”
give it the correct labels, for
为这个流程中的文字检测部分
the text detection part of the pipeline.
直接提供正确的标签
So that, as it, I have
这样好像我就会
a perfect text detection system
有一个非常棒的文字检测系统
on my test One into
能很好地检测我的测试样本
do that run this data
然后我们要做的是
to the rest of five points
继续运行完接下来的几个模块
paper presentation and counter definition.
也就是字符分割和字符识别
And then, use the same
然后使用跟之前一样的
evaluation metric as before,
评价量度指标
to measure what is the
来测量整个系统的
overall accuracy of the entire system.
总体准确度
And with perfect hopefully the performance goes up.
这样用准确的文字检测结果 系统的表现应该会有提升
Let 's say it
假如说 准确率
goes up 89% and then
提高到89%
were going to keep going, next lets
然后我们继续进行
go to the next selection of
接着执行流水线中的下一模块 字符分割
pipeline, two character segmentation and again were going to go to my test.
同前面一样 我还是去找出我的测试集
And now going to
然后现在我不仅用
give the correct text detection
标准的文字检测结果
output and give the correct
我还同时用标准的
character segmentation outputs and
字符分割结果
manually label the correct
所以还是遍历测试样本
segment orientations of text into individual characters.
人工地给出正确的字符分割结果
And see how much that helps.
然后看看这样做以后 效果怎样变化
And let's say it goes up to
假如我们这样做以后
90% accuracy for the overall system.
整个系统准确率提高到90%
Alright so as always the accuracy is.
注意跟前面一样 这里说的准确率
Accuracy of the overall systems.
是指整个系统的准确率
So whatever the final output
所以无论最后一个模块
of the character recognition system is.
字符识别模块给出的最终输出是什么
Whatever the final output of
无论整个流水线的
the overall pipeline is, it's going
最后输出结果是什么
to measure the accuracy of that.
我们都是测出的整个系统的准确率
And then finally like character recognition
最后我们还是执行最后一个模块 字符识别
system and give that the correct label as well.
同样也是人工给出这一模块的正确标签
And if I do that too then, no surprise that I should get a 100% accuracy.
这样做以后 我应该理所当然得到100%准确率
Now, the nice thing about having
进行上限分析的
done this analysis analysis is we
一个好处是
can now understand what is
我们现在就知道了
the upside potential for improving each of these components.
如果对每一个模块进行改善 它们各自的上升空间是多大
So we see that if we get perfect text detection.
所以 我们可以看到 如果我们拥有完美的文字检测模块
Our performance went up from
那么整个系统的表现将会从
72 to 89 percent, so
准确率72%上升到89%
that's' a 17 percent performance gain.
因此效果的增益是17%
So this means that you've
这就意味着
to take your current system you
如果你在现有系统的基础上
spend a lot of time improving text detection.
花费时间和精力改善文字检测模块的效果
That means that we could potentially improve
那么系统的表现
our system's performance by 17 percent.
可能会提高17%
This seems like it's well worth our while.
看起来这还挺值得
Whereas in contrast, when going
而相对来讲
from text detection When we
如果我们取得完美的字符分割模块
gave it perfect character segmentation, performance went up only by one percent.
那么最终系统表现只提升了1%
So, that's a more sobering message.
这便提供了一个很重要的信息
It means that no matter how
这就告诉我们
much time you spend character segmentation,
不管我们投入多大精力在字符分割上
maybe the upside potential is
系统效果的潜在上升空间
going to be pretty small, and maybe
也都是很小很小
you do not want to
所以你就不会让一个
have a large team of engineers
比较大的工程师团队
working on character segmentation that
花时间忙于字符分割模块
this sort of analysis shows that
因为通过上限分析我们知道了
even when you give it the
即使你把字符分割模块做得再好
perfect character segmentation, your
再怎么完美 你的系统表现
performance goes up by only one percent.
最多也只能提升1%
So right there, this is really estimates.
所以这就估计出
What is the ceiling, or what's
通过改善各个模块的质量
an upper bound on how much
你的系统表现
you can improve the performance of your
所能提升的上限值
system by working on one of these components?
或者说最大值 是多少
And finally, going for character,
最后
when we get better
如果我们取得完美的字符识别模块
character recognition, the performance went up by ten percent.
那么整个系统的表现将提高10%
So you know, again you
所以 同样
can decide, is a ten
你也可以分析
percent improvement, how much is that working out?
10%的效果提升值得投入多少工作量
It tells you that maybe
也许这也告诉你
with more efforts spent on the
如果把精力投入在
last station of the pipeline,
流水线的最后这个模块
you can improve the performance
那么系统的性能
of the systems as well.
还是能得到较大的提高
Another way of thinking about this
另一种认识这种分析方法的角度是
is that, by going through this
通过这样的分析
sort of analysis you're trying to
你就能总结出
figure out, you know, what is
改善每个模块的性能
the upside potential, of improving
系统的上升空间是多少
each of these components or how
或者说如果其中的某个模块
much could you possibly gain if
变得绝对完美时
one of these components became absolutely
你能得到什么收获
perfect and just really
这就像是给系统表现
places an upper bound on the performance of that system.
加上了一个提升的上限值
So, the idea of ceiling analysis is pretty important.
所以 上限分析的概念是很重要的
Let me just illustrate this idea again, but with a different example but a more complex one.
下面我再用一个稍微复杂一点的例子来演绎一下上限分析的原理
Let's say that you want to
假如说你想对这张图像
do face recognition from images,
进行人脸识别
so unless you want to look at
也就是说看着这张照片
the picture and recognize whether or
你希望识别出
not the person in this picture
照片里这个人
is a particular friend of yours,
是不是你的朋友
trying to recognize the person shown in this image.
希望辨识出图像中的人
This is a slightly artificial example.
这是一个偏人工智能的例子
This isn't actually how face
当然这并不是现实中的
recognition is done in
人脸识别技术
practice, but I want to step through an example of what a
但我想通过这个例子
pipeline might look like to
来向你展示一个流水线
give you another example of how
并且给你另一个关于
a ceiling analysis process might look.
上限分析的实例
So, we have a
假如我们有张照片
camera image and let's say that we design a pipeline as follows.
我们设计了如下的流水线
Let's say the first thing you want
假如我们第一步要做的
to do is do pre-processing of
是图像预处理
the image, so let's take those
假如我们就用
images like I have shown on
右上角这张照片
the upper right, and let's say we
现在加入我们想要
want to remove the background, so
把背景去掉
through pre-processing the background disappears.
那么经过预处理 背景就被去掉了
Next we want to say detect the face of the person.
下一步我们希望检测出人脸的位置
That's usually done with a learning algorithm.
这通常通过一个学习算法来实现
So we'll run a sliding
我们会运行一个滑动窗分类器
windows crossfire to draw a box around the person's face.
在人脸上画一个框
Having detected the face it
在检测到脸部以后
turns out that if you
如果你想要
want to recognize people it turns
识别出这个人
out that the eyes is a highly useful cue.
那么眼睛是一个很重要的线索
We actually, in terms
事实上
ofrecognizing your friends, the
要辨认出你的朋友
appearance of their eyes is actually
你通常会看眼睛
one of the most important cues that you use.
这是个比较重要的线索
So let's run another crossfire to detect the eyes of the person.
所以 我们需要运行另一个分类器来检测人的眼睛
So, segment out the eyes,
分割出眼睛
and then and since this
这样就提供了
will give us useful features to
识别出一个人的
recognize a person, and then
很重要的特征
other parts of the face of physical interest.
然后继续识别脸上其他重要的部位
Maybe segment out the nose,
比如分割出鼻子
segment out the mouth, and
分割出嘴巴
then, having found the
这样找出了
eyes, the nose and the mouth,
眼睛、鼻子、嘴巴
all of these give us useful
所有这些都是非常有用的特征
features to maybe feed into
然后这些特征可以被输入给某个
a logistic regression crossfire.
逻辑回归的分类器
And it's the job of the
然后这个分类器的任务
crossfire to then give us the
就是给出最终的标签
overall label to find the
找出我们认为能
label for who we think
辨别出这个人是谁的
is the identity of this person.
最终的标签
So this is a kind of complicated pipeline.
这是一个稍微复杂一些的流水线
It's actually probably more complicated
如果你真的想识别出人的话
than you should be using, if you actually want to recognize people.
可能实际的流程比这个还要复杂
But there's an illustrative example that's useful to think about for ceiling analysis.
但这给出了很好的一个上限分析的例子
So how do you go through ceiling analysis for this pipeline?
对这个流水线怎么进行上限分析呢？
Well, we'll step through these pieces one at a time.
我们还是每次关注一个步骤
Let's say your overall system has
假如说你整个系统的准确率
85 percent accuracy, the first
达到了85%
thing I do is go to
那么我要做的第一件事情
my test set and manually
还是找到我的测试集
give it a ground foreground, background,
然后对前景和背景
segmentations, and then manually go to
进行分割
the test set, and use Photoshop
然后使用Photoshop
or something, to just tell it
或者别的什么软件
where's the background, and just
识别出哪些区域是背景
manually remove the background, so
然后手动把背景删掉
ground true background, and see how much the accuracy changes.
然后观察准确率提高多少
In this example, the accuracy
假设在这个例子中
goes up by 0.1%  so
准确率提高了0.1%
this is a strong sign that
这是个很明显的信号
even if you had perfect background
它告诉你即便你
segmentation your performance, even
把背景分割做得很好
if perfect background removal, the
完全去除了背景图案
performance of your system isn't going to go up that much.
但整个系统的表现也并不会提高多少
So this is maybe not worth a
所以似乎并不值得
huge effort to work on pre-processing, on background removal.
花太多精力在预处理或者背景移除上
Then, everything goes to the
接下来 再遍历测试集
test set, given the correct
给出正确的脸部识别图案
face detection images, then again
接下来还是依次运行
step through the eyes, nose, mouth segmentations in some order.
眼睛、鼻子和嘴巴的分割
Pick one order.
选择一种顺序就行了
Let's give the correct location
给出眼睛的正确位置
of the eyes, correct location of
鼻子的正确位置
the nose, correct location of
嘴巴的正确位置
the mouth, and then finally
最后 再给出最终的正确标签
if I just give it the correct overall label, I get 100% accuracy.
准确率提高到100%
And so, you know, as
注意看
I go through the system
在我每次通过这个系统的时候
and just give more and more
我给测试集提供的
components the correct labels
正确的模块越来越多
in the test set, the performance
因此整个系统的表现
So if the overall system goes up,
逐步上升
and you can look at how much
这样你就能很清楚地看到
the performance went up on
通过不同的步骤
different steps, so, you know, from
系统的表现增加了多少
giving it the perfect face detection,
比如 有了完美的脸部识别
and it looks like the overall
整个系统的表现似乎
performance of this system went up by 5.9 percent.
提高了5.9%
So that's a pretty big jump,
这算是比较大的提高了
means that maybe it's worth quite
这告诉你也许在脸部检测上
a bit of effort on better face detection.
多做点努力是有意义的
Went four percent there, went
这里提高4%
one percent there, one percent
这两步都是提高1%
there and three percent there.
这一步提高3%
So it looks like the
所以从整体上看
components that most worth
最值得我付出努力的模块
our while are, when
按顺序排列一下
I gave it perfect face detection,
排在最前的是脸部检测
system went up.
系统表现提高了
By 5.9 performance, might give
5.9%
it perfect eye segmentation, went up
给它完美的眼部分割
by 4%, and then my final logistical
系统表现提高4%
crossfire, well there's another 3 percent gap there maybe.
最终是我的逻辑回归分类器 提高大约3%
And so, this tells us
因此 这很清楚地指出了
maybe one of the components that are most worth our while working on.
哪一个模块是最值得花精力去完善的
And by the way, I
顺便一提
want to tell you, it's a true cautionary story.
我还想讲一个真实的故事
The reason I put in this
我在预处理这里
pre-processing background removal is
放入背景移除这个部分的原因是
because I actually know
我知道一件真实的事情
of a true story where there
原来有一个研究小组
was a research team that actually
大概有两个人
literally had two people spend
不夸张地说
about a year and a half,
花了一年半的时间
spend 18 months, working on
整整18个月
better background removal.
都在完善背景移除的效果
We are rushing here... I am
我不太清楚
obscuring the details for obvious
具体的细节和原因是什么
reasons, but there was a
但确实是有两个工程师
computer vision application where there
为了开发某个
was a team of two engineers
计算机视觉的应用系统
who literally spent I think
大概花了一年半的时间
about a year and a half, working
就为了得到一个
on better background removal.
更好的背景移除效果
Actually they worked out
事实上他们确实研究出了非常复杂的算法
really complicated algorithms, so I ended up publishing I think, one research paper.
貌似最后还发表了一篇文章
But after all that work they
但最终他们发现
found that, it just did
所有付出的这些劳动
not make a huge difference to
都不能给他们研发系统
the overall performance of the
的整体表现带来
actual application they were working on.
比较大的提升
And if only, you know if
而如果要是之前
only someone were to do a [xx] analysis
他们组某个人做一下上限分析
beforehand, maybe we could have realized this.
他们就会提前意识到这个问题
And one of them said to me
后来 他们中有一个人
afterward, you know, if only they
跟我说 如果他们之前
had done the sort of analysis
也做了某种这样的分析
like this, maybe they could
他们就会在长达
have realized before that 18 months
18个月的辛苦劳动以前
of work, that they
意识到这个问题
should have spent their effort focusing
他们就可以把精力花在
on some different component than literally
其他更重要的模块上
spending 18 months working on background removal.
而不是把18个月花在背景移除上
So to summarize, pipelines are
总结一下
pretty pervasive and complex machine learning applications.
流水线是非常常用却又很复杂的机器学习应用
And when you are working on
当你在开发某个
a big machine learning application, I
机器学习应用的时候
mean I think your time as a developer is so valuable.
作为一个开发者 你的时间是相当宝贵的
So just don't waste your
所以真的不要花时间
time working on something that ultimately isn't going to matter.
去做一些到头来没意义的事情
And in this video, we talked
因此在这节课中
about this idea of ceiling analysis,
我给大家介绍了上限分析的概念
which I've often found to
我经常觉得上限分析
be a very good tool for
是个很有用的工具
identifying the component, and if
当你想花精力到某个模块上时
you actually put a focused effort
你可以用上线分析的方法
on that component, and make a
来确定你的努力
big difference, it would actually
会不会产生什么意义
have a huge effect on the
整个系统的表现
overall performance of your final system.
会不会产生明显的提高
So, over the years, working
所以 经过这么多年
with machine learning, I've actually learned
在机器学习中的摸爬滚打
to not trust my own gut
我已经学会了不要凭自己的直觉
feeling about what component to work on.
来判断应该干什么
So, very often, when you have
虽然我从事
worked with machine learning for a
机器学习的工作
long time, but often, our local
已经很多年了
machine learning problem, and I
但经常遇到某个机器学习问题时
may have some gut feeling about,
总有一些直觉告诉我
oh, let's, you know, jump on that component, and just spend more time on that.
我们应该跳到那一个模块 应该把时间花在那儿
That over the years that I
但经过这么多年
have come to even trust my
我现在也开始慢慢意识到
own gut feelings and knowing not
还是不能太相信
to trust gut feelings that much
自己的感觉
and instead really have a
相反地 如果要解决某个机器学习问题
solid machine learning problem, where it's
最好能把问题
possible to structure things.
分成多个模块
To do a ceiling analysis often
然后做一下上限分析
does a much better and much
这通常给你更可靠
more reliable way for deciding
更好的方法
where to put a focused effort
来为你决定
into, to really improve this,
该把劲儿往哪儿使
the performance of some component and
该提高哪个模块的效果
we kind of be sure that when
这样我们就会非常确认
do that it will actually have
把这个模块做好就能提高
a huge effect on the final performance of your process system.
系统的最终表现【果壳教育无边界字幕组】翻译：所罗门捷列夫